here there we go
all right so yeah we were going to talk
about today what was the topic it was
like resiliency
or survival versus
thriving survival mode to
wholeness and my question was a little
bit
what does it mean for a native american
or somebody
very familiar with this language
what does it mean for you to be whole
or to be in survival mode so starting
with survival mode
um i think i'm often in both
simultaneously survival mode is needing
your basic
maslow's needs to be met food clothing
shelter and a lot of times in current
society
even when those needs are being met
we're scared they won't be
right like i don't because i get my food
from a grocery store
i'm reliant on them having food at the
grocery store and i'm also reliant on me
having money to pay for that food at the
grocery store which is very different
than growing intending a garden
that i know is gonna yes the garden
might fail
but the skill the time the the knowledge
is there
to be able to to build it so there's a
certain amount of survival mode that
because i don't have those skills um and
there's also a certain level of survival
mode
that um i tap into each day
based on the fact that like in the
morning i have my highest capacity of
mental emotional and physical
capacity and throughout the day it gets
diminished and so near the end of the
day i'm on survival mode my body feels
like it's being attacked by tigers even
though
logically i know that's not true it
feels like the sights
sounds and smells are so i switch from
survival mode to this wholeness because
i've had to develop a deeper sense of
wholeness
to be able to adapt to that cycle and be
able to get my needs met
within current game a society well not
being able to play game a
so it's it's unique that's it i was
looking forward to this one i liked your
blog post about um
nonsense and the australian who um
australia was one of the words
on their like australian like an alien
australia alien and i was like was that
her best or was
that um no no it's um no
it was just a friend and uh
by thinking and later writing about this
topic of this
video podcast now i was
thinking about this friend
who is really just working six
weeks per year uh making him enough
money to
uh to survive for the rest of the year
and um
he was a little bit upset about his
family um
complaining that he's doing nothing with
you
that he's not working more harder to
make more money
to create more security and things like
this
he used this term nonsense
and for me it is really
a question of liberty if you are able to
do something without any specific
sense just to be in in a flow
or to come into a flow um
by doing some artworks or
or cleaning or whatever it is
it gives me a kind of peace and
and happiness and and and this
i would identify as independent as
something i appreciate a lot
so nonsense is um something like
a signal for the right mode
that something is in the right mode and
the survival mode in in my article
i wrote about this mode because
my experience of the last four months
is that i have every day one or two
calls
of people who are
desperate in finding a place because
even now it's not only a question
of having better food or having
better companionship it's a question of
having any companionship any social life
having any money or anything to eat what
to drink
so a lot of people are losing the job
don't know where they could say
they realized now really what it means
to be in a little family not in this
sick
plants in these big groups like hundred
years ago
so um they are desperate
and they call and they ask they have
their checklist and
this reminds all to this survival mode
no they
they ask how many kids are in your
community
do you have inside jobs can i escape
from the system
is is it possible to be auto
sufficient do you produce what you eat
and drink
and so on so
this is much more than it was one or two
or three years ago
when people asked for a visit of
joining this community
because they themselves are more in
survival mode yeah
and and they feel that um everybody
around them
is also in survival mode so it's um it's
like a general
move movement in the society to
return to this basics so
i get the information that in europe in
many
countries in the first weeks of this
lockdown
everybody was going to um
stores to buy some construction material
because
the european people like to
use free time to work on their houses
on their cars on their facilities
and they enjoyed in the first days
this free extra time to do something
which was on a list for a long
long time and never done and they
they started this so
in the first moment
[Music]
everybody was more relaxed and more
focused
on local private things
their own flat their own car their own
little garden whatever but
after two three months they were
thinking they could return to
their job or all would
become better change
to the normal return to the normal
and they experience it doesn't
it will not return so then they get this
panic
mode then they started
and um i see the same in in the
in the language in in social media when
people are talking in
in groups which are related to community
and community life
the language changed
it's less about dreams and less about
opportunities and nice projects
it's much more about this
fundamental basic things
wondering well you were talking i had
this um
thought of people the survival to
wholeness and i think
a lot of us have experienced that before
we've had our own personal crisis of
like oh i can't survive on my own or i
need to learn how to survive on my own
that we've come through this crisis
before
and that was part there's a bigger
societal piece that most people haven't
gone through
that actually it's society that's like
not able to meet our survival needs and
is not whole
and i think that that is what people are
waking up to and then it puts them into
survival mode right that they're like oh
my god
like there won't be food in the
supermarket there won't be this there
won't be
like they're waking up to how
fragile society is and needing to
like get their individual piece figured
out when really we can't actually figure
it out on a societal like on an
individual or tiny community level
like even as you know even if i have all
the skill to grow my own food and a
beautiful
sustainable community unless we're
willing to kill and die for it
unless other people are fed we're not
safe
right like the world needs to be fed for
my belly to be full
and to feel safety uh from my
perspective
i see everybody even in western
societies growing
up already embedded in a lot of
communities one community is
the global civilization another
community
is the nation the city the village
the street the neighbors maybe some
associations the family a couple
relation
so there are entities of
people and
some of these entities they
painted a very nice picture of security
of
how to to manage a way of life which is
possible
if you follow some rules you get the
benefit of the security and this money
and you achieve what you want and now it
it breaks down and and people realize no
it doesn't work
not in my company not in my society not
in my village
not with this type of politics
okay so um
where else is an entity where
i can get this and i think this is um
in a way a problem we had in germany in
the past
a very controversial politician who said
if i talk the truth they will not vote
for me
if i lie they vote for me
so what i should do so the problem with
a lot of people even people who are
looking now for community life
they are attracted by illusions and
there are
even communities they produce a lot of
solutions
they have nice pictures on their
websites with
people dancing around candles
everybody is singing everybody is happy
everything is
just beautiful so it's like marketing
for a guided tour
through happiness but
i think it will not work as it
as it doesn't work in the big community
it will not work in this little
communities as well but people are
highly attracted by this
because of this component of fear
what they experience they um
they are trapped into this uh very
very limited cycle of
discovering a challenge and trying to
find
as soon as possible a solution for this
and and they they feel they have no time
they need
a solution now and this now
makes them vulnerable for any
kind of advertising which address
this fear
yes i feel it also i also want it now
like i also i've realized in the last
week specifically
but also maybe the week previous to that
how much i
am lacking in the community social
physical connection and even more so
than my needs not being met my kids
needs aren't being met in our current
yeah we're not locked down anymore but
we're kind of locked down
and okay i'll just say that that's my
need that i need to be in
like a rural-ish community where my kids
needs are met and
we can figure out how to get beyond
survival mode together
and i don't know how necessarily to meet
that within our current ability
and yet i know that it is a
a need that like my kid is getting more
and more sad and upset
at current you know situation and it
partly the survival mode
that society is like school's starting
in a month
is it i don't know
nothing's the same nothing's reliable
nothing's old
good informed person but i try to gather
information to find
some milestones or to find some
some lights to navigate
and already
15 years ago the elite
of german companies was
telling that they
expect there will be a future
in 10 20 25 years
where they don't need between 30 and 70
of the employees so this was clear
15 years ago and
there are other things there they are
also
very clear if if you start a project
uh let's think about a company
or any other project you you
you feel with your heart you want to
found an association
you want to set up a community
to solve a problem in a community
or in the society or
you you want to take care about kids
talks
human rights whatever it needs time
when you identify this you you need
some years to make it um
functional in a way so
i am surprised that the people now
are panicking a little bit because
everything of this
not in detail and not maybe
in this massive scale what we
see now in this world but in general
everything of this was clear
even years before now
we talked about the consequences of
a higher average of temperature because
you you can look back in in the history
of this planet
how life was at a time in which it was
much warmer most of the times we had no
ice on
the nautical in this planet history
but we know very well how it was
um in the jungle how many species
we we had and
we know that the pressure of
nature to occupy eomas
in a competition against humanity
is bigger in a on a planet
which has an average of a higher
temperature
so so nothing of this is really a
surprise
so i said five six years ago
to the first visitors of our community
the skills you you will need in the
future
are you need to know what you can eat
and how to find it how to seed
how to find the seeds how to plant it
how to harvest it
and you need the knowledge
and the power to protect it
and this is an ugly truth so it is
not um surprise it is
just um um
maybe this tendency to stick in the
comfort zone
for a lot of people
there's something about what we've done
as a society
and a civilization that of course we all
used to be
tribal and living off the land and and
very
tied to that cycle and we've lost a lot
of that knowledge partly because our
survival has tied to work
right we go we trade hours for dollars
or whatever for dollars
and then trade that for our survival
right and the very things that used to
be
that are the only things required that
were seen during the pandemic like
farmers like you know what i mean the
essential workers
are um the least paid in society
and we're like we want access to that
for cheaper and cheaper
well we and like there's something about
the fact that we
are losing work right work is becoming
less and less of something that is even
usable on like we're coming to the end
of work
as a concept in in our society and
we tie it to our survival in such an
intimate way that when
the wholeness of society comes into
question
our very survival does for real come
into question right this isn't
pretend um you know like
the stress of going to a party feels
like a tiger attacking me this is
actually me and mine starving to death
right like there's an actual real
outcome to that
because we've lost our roots and we've
lost our survival and we've lost and we
can't deal with it
on a personal level anymore like we like
i can go and get the information for how
to survive in the wild in bc
even with that information even if i was
capable of physically hunting and
gardening and doing those things
there isn't enough of that for to
certain for
to sustain the population of bc which
means it's a scarce resource
and we're going to fight over it to the
death like
there's if that's what we're doing right
like
there's a certain amount we that is true
here that is like right we are down to
survival
and there's also a piece that is like
the bullshit of game a of like well
going to a party isn't
a tiger though right and we're so
focused on like the smoke and mirrors
of what it means to like pretend we're
surviving right like no i need that new
car and the instagram post that's
survival
it's like no no no that was never
survival that was never real
but there's this underlining truth of
like right but not having clothes
is fashion's not like but like you need
clothes
you don't need an instagramable meal but
you need calories and nutrition
and there's something about like that
society's waking up to all of these
things at the same time like we're
losing work while we're
tied to our survival well we're losing
like we're learning what
survival isn't and that there's no no
happiness but very little happiness
and real safety in the society that
we've created
and the smoke and mirrors that we're all
so dedicated to keep going
yeah um nearly 60 years ago
there was a publication from club of
rome
about the end of growth so it's
nearly 60 years on this planet that we
know
it's impossible this neoliberalism
idea of never ending growth is
possible more or less at the same time
there was really profound research about
how to develop quality lifetime
which is something we should talk much
more about
not only lifetime we should talk about
quality lifetime
and there is a very clear
relation between the surface of land you
need
to to live to survive in a good way
with good food and
a person and we know from every
continent
and every climber zone we know this
relation in europe the relation is
15 000 square meter per person
so in our community we have
um more than this per person
so we can take this land we can use
part of it as a garden we can use
part of it to harvest some wood for
heating or cooking
and we can let a lot of this land
abandoned
just as a protected
private space like a buffer
for for a future in which maybe we need
to change positions of some
so all this is knowledge known
accessible a lot of years i think
when i listen you that
some of these illusions are specific
illusions of the middle class
the the younger dogs in every society
they are in the survival mode
anyway equal if if you have instagram or
not
they don't care about facebook or a like
or not because they need to find
something to eat for the next day
and it was not changing over the last
200 years for these people in you or in
our society
so the upper class also they
they they have the cake and they can't
understand that not everybody has cake
like this famous quote of this french
princess so um
it was a middle class and the middle
class was
convinced by making money
following this this pass
to solve everything in an individual way
and now they realize it's not possible
i think 10 years ago i made an artwork
and i
quoted
i think therefore ib
as as an old quote i changed
or i felt i have to change
in i upload to be so
a lot of people in this middle class um
they feel really dead if they lose
their facebook account or whatever
social media access
so i think this is something which has
to
um to be
evaluated and we have to find
a different answer to why we are on this
planet i would not say that we have
less to do there is less work it's just
not
paid work so when i look
out of the window 50 in germany
of what i see when i look out of my
window
is done by people
on a basis of a volunteer who just
offer something for the public for
a kind of community cleaning the street
taking some rubbish out of the park
nothing of this is paid
working with kids football teams leading
football teams
all these jobs are unpaid and all this
is
part of this beauty what i see when i
look outside of this window
so 50 of what i see
was already not paid anymore
but it is the reality and if i want this
um i i i should not think about reducing
this
work i should think about redefining
what it means to live to be my values
um and to find um
a contract in the community of a society
which leads to
to quality lifetime
i had a note here and i don't know what
it actually says
farming go back to farming that's what
it was
um that is exactly what i mean when i
mean the end of work
i don't mean the end like we all get to
sit around have unlimited leisure time
although yes that's also what i mean
it's that
that labor isn't done we just choose to
use our labor
for our and our collective benefit and
we get to choose instead of it being
tied to survival
right that we have to change the
survival is so intimately
intertwined with our work our sense of
being is intimately intertwined with
that
and so if we're losing work and we are
kind of collectively on an economic
level right like small businesses are
going under
big corporations are taking more of the
power in jobs and therefore they have
more collective power to pay us less and
so
and things are being automated and
there's real and at the same time
we still need the same amount of
calories we still have art we still have
like there's never an
end to that and there's something about
again our history of society that we did
all used to be farmers and it was a hard
arduous life
and now it's like that leave that to
them and we get to
you know we we're on instagram instead
of actually having our hands in the dirt
when really
there's a quality to life about having
your hands in the dirt
that you can't get
through it like you can't get that right
like you can't go to the grocery
market and get the satisfaction of
growing your own food
it's just not they're not the same thing
but what we hear
as people on instagram in game a is you
want me to go back to toi like my my
life is so intimately tied all i know is
instagram all i know is this like very
particular work function i can only type
i can do excel spreadsheets i can do
like that's not growing in food and what
you want me to do is give that
up to go back it's like no we can get
this needs met as a as a collective
right as however big your collective is
one to billions of people
we can get our needs met and then you
can choose to focus
your instead of being on survival what
do you do from a state of fullness right
what do
how do we get you whole as whole as you
can be and
what do you contribute from that because
the more whole we are the more we do
contribute like we're in this
smoking mirrors broken game that the
more of us wake up to that and
don't and can
can honor how hard it is to wake up to
that right that what people hear is you
want them to go be farmers when they're
on instagram and they're not
quite the same as like right and they're
waking up to the fact that instagram
isn't going to get their needs met so
they're in survival mode looking for
anywhere that can get their needs met
when their needs can't be met right like
if you don't know
you don't your instagram skills aren't
really needed in this new world and yet
they are
i could use someone's instagram skills
to do what i'm doing but like there's
something about the people are in
survival mode
and they feel like when you're telling
them or getting into game b
whatever their version of game b is
they're gonna have to give up everything
that they care about
and that's not true they actually get a
hell of a lot more
right like like i said there is
something about growing your own food
that gives you something if you're being
forced to that's a completely different
scenario
you have to toil in the fields for 40
hours it's different than
as a collective we're doing this and
we're sharing the food and we get good
food and
you get to be in community and and
there's just there's something
you can't put it in a textbook right
like you have to be in it to get that
and there's something yeah but i i think
you can say something about this
tragedy of the people so if you see all
this like a
labyrinth and you want to
arrive to an area
where you can try to
to explore
game b like alternative entities
and constructions so you want to go out
of
this game a you feel this
emptiness so you are searching for the
right way if you see it like this
so um every time you have the decision
to the left to the right
straight ahead so you do this and you
run
in a in a on a in front of a wall you
can't
you have to go back so what you do in
your strategy is you go back
as long as you don't meet an alternative
road you could go then
you take the alternative row if
this doesn't work as
the first one you step back deeper
so you go back to the
um to to the point of the
previous decision and you do this as
long as you need to do it to find
another way
so my big question for game b
is um
where is the relation between game a and
money and
game b and money
how deep i need to go back okay um
to find game b and my
thesis is um it doesn't
it doesn't help us to
to find the better construction of a
company
or to find the better construction of
the association
another entity who produce something
[Music]
if all is calculated by money and
money is the currency to evaluate
benefits losses
advantages disadvantages and so on
uh we we don't arrive
so when you first brought up the
labyrinth one you were talking about
going back and then
you take the other alternative route my
brain was like well what if the first
option was wrong
right like if there's two you can go
left or right and you go right
and you're never making it to the center
of the labyrinth because left was the
way right so every other way that you go
you have to get back to that very first
choice to
pick the right way i think game b is not
a physical
structure of a labyrinth where you're
trying to get to the center
it is a ever-changing labyrinth where if
you ch
if you chose the wrong version to begin
with it's
rearranging itself to help you find the
right one
and so there is something about trying
like if we're just trying to fix game a
it's very much that it's going back to
one fourth and being like okay let's try
this little tweak let's try this out
and thinking that like there's something
about then the other options to go back
to the first one and take the right
instead of the left or vice versa um
where
there's something about game b that has
to work within game a so it has to work
within the labyrinth that was created to
begin with
but what we don't realize is there it's
it's this nebulous flowing thing that
actually helps us figure it out and you
can't even get to that metaphor within
the labyrinth because
it breaks the labyrinth you know what i
mean like if a labyrinth is constantly
changing and there's no point in getting
to the center it's not a labyrinth
like it's not one solution it's not
let's put it um let's try it in another
way
to be able to have any sensation
of being more close to game b
you need the kind of memory
and knowledge you already received
in your life to be able to evaluate this
so in one social network conversation i
asked
a woman do you ever experience
a game b like relation
between you and somebody else
do you have an answer
yeah i i mean i live my life like that
so i constantly try to
have only game b relationships ones that
aren't transactional
or we're not trading money or dealing in
that realm
but they're not necessarily in that
right so i have people in my community
who um i dog sit for them
because i want to be in the community
and i really like their dog and everyone
in their place
and they want to pay me for it i'm like
i don't want to be paid for it because
i'm getting something out of it
and it turns it into a transaction where
i'm your employee
instead of and yet they have money and i
don't so there's some like there's
something about
i'm like right and that makes me even
less want to take your money like i'm
like i want
to be doing you a favor and you're doing
me a favor by me staying here and not
it be a tit for t like there's and yet
there's something in their energy then
of like oh but if we make it a
transaction it's easier we know how to
deal with that
right we know this for that and so
it's a different like i'm like i'm
looking for everywhere that i can give
within my capacity while finding a way
to get my needs met without necessarily
tying them together
and society is not big on that though
right like and this is part of the
survival versus
fullness is my wholeness is very much
both i'm in survival and wholeness both
constantly and
my unique gift on this planet i believe
is to help create game b
but in a way that's like i'm not whole
by myself i can't be
i have to fit with other people to be
able to do a project to be able to live
in community to be able to do those
things
and um that to me is game b
like it's not one person being able to
do everything okay i got the way to the
labyrinth let's go
it's like how do we come together and
actually figure out governance how do we
come together and figure out how to
solve things how do we
um figure it out from this space because
this is the other thing with the
labyrinth one
is capitalism is very or what i game a
is very much we have a problem so we
solve it that's a right or a left and
then you need to go back to it so if
money is one of the first turns right so
yes money is completely broken but in
order to
fix money you'd have to go back so far
you'd break all of society
because as we've taken these turns we've
designed society around them right it's
like well we need money so now
everything's focused on money
but there is a way to restructure the
labyrinth within the
like to create game b within game a
we're using money against
itself um and then eventually game a
goes away because game b has created
something that is omni-win
and etsy rivalries and game a can't
compete with that they just can't
but it has to be done from within this
current one and it's hard because we're
in a physical
labyrinth and what we're trying to do is
get to the center and we don't even know
that that's not
because it's moving and changing and
nebulous and like you can't go back and
then take a different fork because it
makes everything else
fall away and so you have to change you
have to take all the forks at the same
time
right you can't just you can't really go
back and take that other fork
you have to go back and take the money
forward and do this for can do that for
you can't
because our entire society is set up
like that way and otherwise we're all
gonna get into tribal mode and be at war
with each other and ourselves
so there has to be a way to within
safety and um
happiness within feeling like where our
needs are met
be able to figure out that labyrinth
together and luckily
the universe is kind of there to help
with that in a way but it takes a faith
to believe that like it takes it but
it shows up that it continually happens
that way like it's like
i'm someone who wants the labyrinth i
want to figure it out logically
map it and give it to everyone else and
it can't it's not that way it's a
different path for everyone to get to
the center
and we're not even getting into the same
center
uh okay so our experience
in familia feliz in this little
community
is that we don't
need money
to regulate something and we don't think
so much
in money it doesn't mean that
we are not a part of game a
societies and communities so we have to
contribute
to pay water to pay light and so on and
so on
but the general aspect
is that we try to establish
relations between people which are
for me game bae like game b like
relations like the relation between a
mother and a child
you don't give birth and put a debt on
the bank account of your kid
you it's not a college uh situation
um you you give milk to this kid
you um you uh
cook you educate and so on and so on and
all this
you don't do to create a dependence
uh which you might want to use later
for your personal benefit you do this
because you want
your kid as much as independent from you
so our community is designed like this
so we have no products we have no
associations we have no
no companies or enterprises running
as a community
on the level of a member everybody of us
is free to do it and some of us
are freelancers or employees
or they run little companies
but they do this on a personal level but
on the level of the community
we don't think in terms of money
we think in terms of donation and this
means
like with this sample with the mother
and the kid
it turns out that we
empower each other
we create more liberty for each other
on the midterm and on a long term
and even now in this time of
the corona crisis of this lockdown
our experience is we have much
more quality of life than others
because this way of not
following the money means that we
um we are not so much
touched by what happened now in the
economy
because a lot of things a lot of our
networks
are already established without
this uh this for that without
these deals without this looking for the
the benefit or for the advantage so we
we didn't
we didn't try to optimize the kind of
product
we tried to optimize this
liberty and um this
the social behavior and even the joy and
the happiness
embedded in donating something without
expectation
and um this looks
now looking backwards as
as a very nice protection in this
uh situation so
survival to me
like being able to survive in a whole
state is being able to have my
very basic needs met whether
individually or collectively i know i
can't meet them individually so i need
to make them meet them collectively
there's something in society that we did
right this specialization
has given us game a in a very big way
and there's a good side to that and
maybe not so good side to that but
specialization has given us
what we have right if we if we didn't
have electric shit we wouldn't need to
have engineers and
fixers and such but i like having
electronic stuff
like there's a certain level of having
the complexity and the complicated
means we need specialization because my
question is what do you mean by
independence
um that every person has the capacity to
feed themselves even without the
community within the community or
like with this trade-off of
specialization and complexity
what do you mean by independence
independence in in
my view is
the relation between
two people inside embedded in a
community
and between one of this person
focusing the community as an entity
and in both ways um i want to expand
independence and um i can do this
from the side of the community if
everything which is organized
is organized in the way that it doesn't
lead
to dependence and on the individual way
i can do this if i for example donate
without expectation which means
there is no payback there is no risk
there is no risk to take
because there is no balance sheet
i have to to follow later on
this is a way of independence and the
other independence
is that
everybody can
try to find a balance between his own
skills
on one side and
on the other side the needs
of other members in the community
so my question is
what i'm able to do what i
should learn because i see there is a
need
inside of the community
this is something
which is on my individual side and it
doesn't mean that
finally everybody take the same
hours in the garden and everybody take
the same
uh screen time uh making programmation
uh and so on and so on uh no it means
that um everybody try
first what is easy for him
to do this is uh very efficient
uh because he need less time than
another one
and the second is to see okay
if we need a plumber and nobody is able
to do it
who might be willing to learn
that's the thing but everything
of this um is um
based on this general idea like
in your situation as a mother with a kid
you want the maximum of independence for
your kid
you want to charge it with knowledge
you want to give a good starting point
and you want to release it with a
maximum
what you can gather
and this is our
approach in the relation between the
community
and an individual member of the
this is this form of
independence we like to see in
communities
and if if it's a guru driven
community for sure you will not find
this
because this project
should not
end with independent followers
it should end with with a very clear
hierarchy and dependence and this is not
what we what we want
it's interesting because part of and
this is something i wanted to get into
from reading your article this last week
but maybe we'll make it for the topic
next week because we're going to come
down to the hour um of that you just
said something but like you never really
do anything for the community itself you
only do things for other individuals and
i'm thinking of the community i'm part
of and i'm like
what like there's somebody who is
amazing at the compost it's like his
genius and he's doing it constantly
um if he left that is a role that would
have to be filled by somebody
and yet he fills it so perfectly we
would never find someone who fills that
role
the same way he does and um he is giving
it to
the community right like he's not
composting for me as an individual
and yet he is like that's the weird like
i get it and i don't get it
and um there's something about like the
need of the community needs to so
what i propose for a topic for next week
is this um
conversation between the individual in
the community
that like the community as an individual
like it's it's an entity in and of
itself
and it's a con it's a composition of a
bunch of individuals with their own
personal right to have independence
means that the person in charge of
composting can leave and go to a
different community
to meet his own needs right without
without feeling that
restraint of like the community's not
going to know how to call those
yes they will you will train you know
maybe like there's
something there yeah so it will propose
like the difference between individual
and community
yeah but
[Music]
see every maybe also from another
perspective
um if you imagine you have a community
and
somebody is has very very high skills
in in gardening and
this person is leaving the community
so you lose this qualification
you suffer a lot as a community
what does it mean it is the same like
when you see in in the in a city like
detroit or other cities
you have a lot of abandoned places there
was industrial areas a lot of
work a lot of dreams of any
kind of future and now it's wasteland
looks very sad could be
so nice but it's not yeah this is the
resource
this is a kind of compost of tomorrow
so i think you have to accept even in a
community that you will
not be perfect and you will miss this
[Music]
this knowledge in this sample
and you will suffer from it but
try to invent some rules contracts
or a kind of dependence
to catch this gardener to make him so
weak that he is frightened
to lose the contact to the community
because
maybe he's not able to drive a car and
he loses the opportunity to go shopping
with somebody
or other things whatever you imagine all
these
are typical strategies in game a
and i think they don't lead to this
independence
so our community
is a very very reduced entity
and finally it doesn't exist
familiar feliz is an idea
and it doesn't become anybody
anybody in terms of your restriction
of law um like an
enterprise or company or association or
co-op or whatever you think
and it doesn't become a body as
[Music]
as as a yeah
as a group of people who want to make a
kind of business together
it is just an idea but every
um interaction between our members
is clearly an interaction one to one
all the time one to one the idea
brings us together in in a in a physical
place
in our homes in our gardens and it
brings us together in an intellectual
place if we use social media
or other platforms to communicate but
um we enjoy
a lot to have a very weak
entity of community because
this makes space from very
powerful members and we think this
powerful member
this powerful individual embedded in
this idea
is is this synthesis
between this western north american
european way of finding happiness
and this asian african
way of finding happiness only in
community
we think we need to integrate both
to find this
all right i think that's a probably good
place to end it are you open to having
next week be individual in community
then it sounds like there's a lot of um
stuff dissociate i like the idea i'm
just gonna
what you said about the mother and child
like that you're
as a good parent you're trying to make
your kid independent you're trying to
make them so they don't need you someday
and everything we do to not be right
where it's like oh i need my kid to be
more dependent on me so she comes back
so i do laundry for her constantly right
like when you're
in university there's nothing wrong in
and of itself with that but it's not
making your kid
independent so they can choose to come
back right so
you're like oh and in that choice is
like it's
hard as a community to think you're
going to lose someone and so you do kind
of want to like hold them back
and to to the biggest reason that
happens i think is we don't acknowledge
it
right that it's like oh well if this
person leaves we're not going to have
something to do compost therefore you
can't leave therefore
right let's not let's make sure they're
not able to do anything but
that one function and there's something
beautiful about
making sure as a community you're strong
as an individual you're strong so
everyone has a choice you can be there
if you want to be
leave if you want to be and we'll
survive
and there's something also about as an
individual
you think you know yourself and your
skills and your your limitations but
those
also change throughout your life just
like the community changes
you lost your composter it's like you
lost your right arm you lost
your ability you know like your
cognitive ability you gained this
skill you lost this one that there's a
flow to it
a lot a lot of people they they uh
invent a kind of narrative for a
community
this narrative narrative could be
religion for example
or health or other topics
and um you want to gather the people you
want to bind the people to this
community
because you try to invent something
which is higher than the person
and we don't do this we have
nothing of this um
uh we and and this is the kind of
peace and the kind of happiness
we we can realize
out of this independence so
so what when you make it in in one
sentence what is um
the question for the next session i
didn't make it in the form of a question
but the topic is individual versus
sounds wrong but individual in community
right the individual and the group i
don't know if you're familiar with the
integral work
but the idea that like you transcend and
include an
individual versus the group but like the
community this is going to go against a
little bit what you're saying but like
the community is itself an individual
right and then it's a it's part of a
bigger community of communities
theoretically whether it's part of it or
not right there's other communities to
interact with
there's the individual but there's also
like you make up a bunch of communities
right like
your heart and your nervous system or
your you know
church community like that there's parts
of the individual in parts of the group
so i realized i just made a very
big sentence the topic is individual and
community
and encompassing that right that
this is the topic to be do we transcend
and include
right do we have is the community its
own entity
is there a benefit to looking at it as
its own entity and i like what you're
going where i haven't even thought like
of not necessarily having in its own
entity because it gives it
a different quality which i'm seeing
like yeah okay i get that
and so getting into that individual and
the community
whose role what right is the community
just a group of individuals
individuals just people seeking
community like
what is what makes one what makes the
other what are the
properties that are one another very
open conversation from that right
okay so we we talked um in the beginning
about
um the
using this video podcast for
gathering more people or more attention
in social media also
i'm surrounded in the last days by
more and more people because every time
i write a little article about this
topic
and the people are curious
to see this video as well so i would
like to see it in public and i would
like to
to use this form also to
uh to find more to enrich the discussion
by having more different opinions
yeah i i'm down with this one being
public for sure um
and i think we did talk about them all
being public i think daniel and linda
will be okay with that as well as well
as i just want to mention
uh you're welcome to invite any of those
people to if they're available during
this time period right that this is an
open
conversation that anyone can come and be
part of those are
generally what i'm looking to do is not
create a broadcast conversation that
people watch
but create a space that people can come
and be part of a conversation because
they
they get something out of it right like
its own its own entity
you are still um
yeah i can stop recording